Register of the Free Europe Press issuances
Hoover Institution Archives
Free Europe Press issuances
1951-1956
2010C11
Free Europe Press.
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
American propaganda leaflets and bulletins, distributed by balloon to Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Poland. Includes some English-language working material versions.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2010.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
In the 1950s, at the height of the Cold War, numerous psychological warfare leaflets were prepared by the Free Europe Press (FEP) of the Free Europe Committee. The group worked in cooperation with Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty, with the U.S. Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) funding much of the operations.
FEP leaflets were a major part of the post-World War II psychological warfare battle between East and West. The operation sent 590,415 balloons that carried 301,636,883 leaflets, posters, books, and other printed matter from West Germany over the Iron Curtain to Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Poland from August 1951 to November 1956.
These documents urged peasants to refuse to cooperate with collective farms and exhorted Slovaks and Czechs to boycott national elections. They included embarrassing secret memoranda suppressed by Communist governments.
Source: Free Europe Press Cold War Leaflets, Accessed 2012 http://www.psywarrior.com/RadioFreeEurope.html
Scope and Content of Collection
American propaganda leaflets and bulletins, distributed by balloon drop over Czechoslovakia, Hungary and Poland. Includes some English-language working material versions.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Propaganda, American--Europe, Eastern.
Collection Contents
- Czechoslovakia, 1951-1956 (Box 1)
  - First launch, Operation "Winds of Freedom,", 1951 (Box 1)
    - Poselství Čechům a Slovákům (Folder 1: 1)
    - Poselství Čechům a Slovákům: Přátelê! (Folder 1: 2)
    - Pravda o vlaku svobody (Folder 1: 3)
  - Second launch, Operation "Prospero,", 1953 (Box 1)
    - Vzpoura ve Východním Nĕmecku (Folder 1: 4)
    - Hladová koruna / Všchen nas lid zasvobodu [false currency] (Folder 1: 5)
  - Third launch, Operation "Veto" and subsequent operations, April 1954-June 1956 (Box 1)
    - Stickers: 8 designs, related to "10 požiadaviek" (Folder 1: 6)
    - Kandidátka lidovê oposice (Folder 1: 7)
    - Kandidátka lúdovej opozície (Folder 1: 8)
    - V jednote sila / V jednotĕ síla (Folder 1: 9)
    - Stickers: 2 designs, žatva sebaobrany národa / žnĕ (Folder 1: 10)
    - Lidová oposice vyhlašuje žnĕ sebeobrany národa (Folder 1: 11)
    - Konec selskê roboty! (Folder 1: 12)
    - Našim robotníkom! [Trade union leaflet] (Folder 1: 13)
    - Skoncovat so sedliackym poddanstvom! [Farmers] (Folder 1: 14)
    - Českí a slovenskí rolníci! [Farmers leaflet #2] (Folder 1: 15)
    - Československým dĕlníkům! [Trade union leaflet, #2] (Folder 1: 16)
    - Stalinova modla se kácí (Folder 1: 17)
    - Osvobození ujařmených národů? [Eisenhower Christmas Speech, December 1955] (Folder 1: 18)
    - Vánočni pozdrav [Booklet of Christmas materials, 1955] (Folder 1: 19)
    - Projev N.S. Chruščeva [Khrushchev speech to 20th party congress, February 1956] (Folder 1: 20)
    - Svobodná Evropa: českým a slovenským rolníkům [to Czech and Slovak farmers] (Folder 1: 21)
    - Svobodná Evropa: mládeži [youth] (Folder 1: 22)
    - Demokratický průvodce Prahou [guide to Prague] (Folder 1: 23)
    - Stickers: Czechoslovak and U.S. flags, with motto (Folder 1: 24)
    - Unidentified translation of leaflet (Folder 1: 25)
    - Svobodná Evropa / Slobodna Európa: newsletters, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
      - Svobodná Evropa: Prvních deset, Kvĕten 1954 (Folder 1: 26)
      - Slobodná Európa: Desa? požiadaviek, Máj 1954 (Folder 1: 27)
      - Zvláštni vydani (Folder 1: 28)
      - No. 14: Zač bojujeme?, May 1954 (Folder 1: 29)
      - No. 15: Útok na obou frontách (Folder 1: 30)
      - No. 16: Nebude novĕho mnichova (Folder 1: 31)
      - No. 17: Jde to a půjde to (Folder 1: 32)
      - No. 18: Poučenie a povzbudenie (Folder 1: 33)
      - No. 19: O kurs opravdu nový (Folder 1: 34)
      - No. 20: Režim v úzkych (Folder 1: 35)
      - No. 21: O našem tisku (Folder 1: 36)
      - No. 22: Čo sa deje u susedov (Folder 1: 37)
      - No. 23: Nejsou volby jako volby (Folder 1: 38)
      - Kalendář Svobodnê Evropy, 1955 (Folder 1: 39)
      - No. 24: Odbory?co jsou a co nejsou (Folder 1: 40)
      - No. 25: Cesta, kterou jsme ušli (Folder 1: 41)
      - No. 26: Obrana európy (Folder 1: 42)
      - No. 27: Po staru se že nedá (Folder 1: 43)
      - No. 28: Pokrok a reakcia (Folder 1: 44)
      - No. 29: Ztracený monopol (Folder 1: 45)
      - No. 30: Bilancia ludovêho boja (Folder 1: 46)
      - No. 31: Hráz se zpevňuje (Folder 1: 47)
      - No. 32: Sjezd československêho lidu (Folder 1: 48)
      - No. 33: Všetkêho do času (Folder 1: 49)
      - No. 34: Začíná se nova kapitola (Folder 1: 50)
      - No. 35: Národní sebeobrannê žnĕ, 1955 (Folder 1: 51)
      - No. 38: October 1955 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 52)
      - No. 39: November 1955 [Czech] (Folder 1: 53)
      - No. 40: November 1955 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 54)
      - No. 41: [Czech] (Folder 1: 55)
      - No. 42: New Year's, 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 56)
      - No. 43: January 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 57)
      - No. 45: February 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 58)
      - No. 46: March 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 59)
      - No. 47: April 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 60)
      - No. 48: May 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 61)
      - No. 49: May 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 62)
      - No. 50: June 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 63)
      - No. 51: June 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 64)
      - No. 52: July 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 65)
      - No. 53: August 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 66)
      - No. 54: August 1956 [Slovak] (Folder 1: 67)
      - No. 55: September 1956 [Czech] (Folder 1: 68)
- Hungary, 1954-1956. (Box 2)
  Includes Operation "Focus"
  - Nemzeti Ellenállási Mozgalom (Folder 2: 1)
  - Stickers: 12 various designs; N.E.M., 12 Követelês (Folder 2: 2)
  - A fold azê, aki megműveli! [Kolkhoz leaflet] (Folder 2: 3)
  - Az új tanácsok tagjaihoz! [local council leaflet] (Folder 2: 4)
  - Christmas message (Folder 2: 5)
  - Húsvêti üzenet [Easter message] (Folder 2: 6)
  - A falu nêpêhez! [Kolkhoz leaflet, #2] (Folder 2: 7)
  - április 4 ["Liberation" anniversary, 1954] (Folder 2: 8)
  - Pusztul-e verge Rákosi? (Folder 2: 9)
  - Stickers: Depicting statue of Stalin falling on Rákosi (Folder 2: 10)
  - Sticker: Depicting Saint Steven (Szent István), comparing him with Cardinal Mindszenty (Folder 2: 11)
  - Az írástudók lázadása [Special literary leaflet] (Folder 2: 12)
  - Nyikita Szergejevics Hruscsov [Khrushchev's speech at the 20th Party Congress, February 1956] (Folder 2: 13)
  - Egy Amerikás Magyar beszámol (Folder 2: 14)
  - Az amerikai külpolitika cêlja? [Labor leaflet] (Folder 2: 15)
  - Szabad Magyarország (newsletter), 1954-1956 (Folder 2:)
    - No. 1 (Folder 2: 16)
    - No. 2 (Folder 2: 17)
    - No. 2, Second edition (Folder 2: 18)
    - No. 3, Tovább az úton (Folder 2: 19)
    - No. 4, Bukás után (Folder 2: 20)
    - No. 5 (Folder 2: 21)
    - No. 6, Az elhajlók pártja (Folder 2: 22)
    - No. 7, A kommunisták szennyese (Folder 2: 23)
    - No. 9, Hazaárnlok! (Folder 2: 24)
    - No. 11, A bêke ügye (Folder 2: 25)
    - No. 12, Genfi szellem (Folder 2: 26)
    - No. 13, Konferenciák idejên (Folder 2: 27)
    - No. 14, Külön utakon (Folder 2: 28)
    - No. 15, Jobb kollektív szerződêst (Folder 2: 29)
    - No. 16, Nyílt beszêd (Folder 2: 30)
    - No. 17, Moszkvában elhatározták, hogy ezentúl minden máskêppen volt (Folder 2: 31)
    - No. 18, Röplapokkal hazugságok ellen (Folder 2: 32)
    - No. 19, Hős Lengyelország (Folder 2: 33)
- Poland, 1955-1956. (Box 2)
  Includes Operation "Spotlight"
  - Folwark zwierz?cy [Animal Farm, by George Orwell] (Folder 2: 34)
  - Wybrałem prawd? (I), by Seweryn Bialer (Folder 2: 35)
  - Wybrałem prawd? (II), by Seweryn Bialer (Folder 2: 36)
  - Przemówienie N.S. Chruszczowa [Khrushchev's speech at 20th Party Congress, 1956] (Folder 2: 37)
  - O sprawiedliwość dla prześladowanych (Folder 2: 38)
  - Głosy za świata (Folder 2: 39)
  - Za kulisami bezpieki I partii (Folder 2: 40)
  - Wolna Europa (newsletter), 1955-1956 (Box 2)
    - No. 1, October 1955, "Prez. Eisenhower-o narodach ujarzmionych" (Folder 2: 41)
    - Special edition, January 1956 (Folder 2: 42)
    - No. 2, February 1956, "Wyzwolenie narodów ujarzmionych?celem polityki USA" (Folder 2: 43)
    - No. 3, March 1956, "Czyny nie słowa" (Folder 2: 44)
    - No. 4, June 1956, "Członek Centralnogo Aktywu PZPR ujawnia" (Folder 2: 45)
    - No. 7, September, 1956, "Przebieg wypadków Poznańskich" (Folder 2: 46)